《(雪乃)
もう無理して来なくていいわ》
You don't have to force yourself to attend anymore.
(クラクション)
≪(平塚)な～に 合同イベントまで
あと１週間だろ？➡
Well, the joint event is a week away, right?
様子を見に行ったら
もう終わってたんでな➡
So I went to check on the meeting, but it was already over.
私も帰ろうと思っていたところで
君を見つけたんだ
I was on my way home when I found you.
(比企谷)はあ
Oh.
先生 こんな車でしたっけ？
Is this the car you drive?
夏休みの時と違うような…
It doesn't look like the one you had in summer...
ああ あれはレンタカーだよ➡
Oh, that was a rental.
私の愛車は こいつだ
This baby's mine.
比企谷
うん？
Hikigaya...
少し 寄り道していいか？
Mind if we make a little stop?
♬～
(平塚の鼻歌)
着いたぞ
Here we are.
うん？
Mihama
Bridge
l
v
I won't lose!
<3 Nakamura
Yuu & Saki
Celebrating 4 months together
We'll be together forever
比企谷
うん？
Hikigaya!
…っと
You look kinda cool like that.
何か かっこいいっすね
かっこつけてるからな
Because I'm trying to look cool.
So, how are things going?
どうかね？ 調子は
結構ヤバそうです
It's looking pretty bad.
What's looking bad?
ふむ 何がヤバい？
It's hard to say exactly...
何がって言われても
一概には…
まあ 話してみたまえ
Well, try telling me anyway.
Okay...
はあ
Then...
じゃあ
問題は時間ですかね
I guess time is the problem.
あと１週間で
この現状を覆せる気がしない
I don't see how we can turn this situation around in a week.
玉縄と一色
あいつらは怖いんですよ
Tamanawa and Isshiki are both scared
自分のせいで失敗することが
to think of this thing failing because of them.
だから 責任を分散させるために
So, to distribute the responsibility, they ask for others' opinions
人の意見を求め それを取り入れる
and try to implement those.
And the result is this plateau we're stuck on.
その結果が停滞した この現状で
We were wrong not to decide
誰が一番上で
who's on top, and who should bear the responsibility.
誰が一番責任を負うのかを
決めなかったことが
そもそもの間違いだった
まあ そんな感じですかね
I guess that's about it.
よく見ている
You have a good eye.
君は人の心理を
読み取ることには長けているな
You're very good at reading people's mental states.
そんなこと…
けれど
I'm not...
But...
感情は理解していない
You don't understand emotions.
One's mental state and the emotions they feel aren't always equal.
心理と感情は
常にイコールじゃない
時に全く不合理に見える結論を
出してしまうのは そのせいだ
That's why they sometimes reach conclusions that seem completely illogical.
だから雪ノ下も由比ヶ浜も 君も
That's why Yukinoshita, Yuigahama, and you
間違えた答えを出す
all give wrong answers, too.
いや あいつらのことは今
関係なくないですか
Uh, they have nothing to do with this, do they?
They're the ones I was asking you about in the first place.
私は 最初から
彼女達のことを聞いたつもりだ
だが まあ 本質はどちらも同じだ
But, well...
In essence, they're both the same.
問題の根っこは一つなんだよ
Both problems have the same root.
心だ
It's in the heart.
けど それって考えて分かるもん
じゃないじゃないですか
But that's not something you can understand by thinking, is it?
分からないか？
You don't understand?
Then think harder.
なら もっと考えろ
計算しかできないなら
計算しつくせ
If you can only think in terms of calculations, then calculate it.
全部の答えを出して
消去法で一つずつ潰せ
Lay out all the answers,
and knock them out one by one via process of elimination.
What's left, in the end, is your answer.
残ったものが 君の答えだ
それでも分かるもんじゃ
ないんじゃないですかね？
Still, it's not something you can really understand, is it?
Then either you calculated wrong, or you missed something.
なら 計算が間違っているか
見落としがあるんだろ
また計算のやり直しだな
You just have to calculate it all over again.
あんた ムチャクチャだ
バカ者
You're nuts.
You imbecile.
感情が計算できるなら
とっくに電脳化されてる
If emotions could be calculated, they'd have been digitized by now.
計算できずに残った答え
The answer left behind because you couldn't calculate it
それが人の気持ちというものだよ
is what you call "human emotion."
Of course, I say that,
まあ そういう私も
計算違いばかりしているから
but it's probably because I keep miscalculating that I can't get married...
結婚できないんだろうけどな
この前も
友達の結婚式があってな…
Just the other day, my friend got married...
No, that's because the guys you know have lousy taste.
いや そりゃ相手に
見る目がないんですよ
えッ？
Huh?
If I'd been born ten years earlier...
<俺が あと10年早く生まれていて>
If I'd met her ten years earlier,
<あと10年早く出会っていたら>
I probably would've fallen madly in love with her.
<たぶん心底
ホレていたんじゃないかと思う>
<そんな仮定に意味はないけれど>
Not that there's any point in hypothesizing about it.
Wh-Where'd that come from?
何だ 急に
N-Never mind...
まあいい 礼というのもなんだが
特別にヒントをあげよう
I wouldn't call it thanking you, but I'll give you a hint.
(せき払い)
考える時は 考えるべきポイントを
間違えないことだ
When you think, don't pinpoint the wrong thing to think about.
For example...
例えば 君が奉仕部としてではなく
The reason you're helping Isshiki individually,
単独で一色を手伝っている理由
and not as part of the Service Club.
Try thinking about that.
これについて考えてみよう
For the Service Club's sake,
これは奉仕部のため
あるいは雪ノ下のためだ
or in other words, for Yukinoshita's sake.
It's plain to see.
見ていれば分かるよ
選挙の一件のあと
Yukinoshita came to report to me after the election.
雪ノ下が報告にきた
She won't talk about herself,
あの子は
自分のことを話してはくれないが
but just watching her, I thought it might be the case.
様子を見て もしかしたらと思った
それは君も同じか？
Does that go for you, too?
Uh... er... I don't know...
ああ いや どうですかね
If you had the same thing in mind,
もし君が
同じ考えを抱いたとすれば
彼女達を傷つけないために
遠ざけるという考えに行き着く
you might arrive at the idea of distancing
yourself from them so you wouldn't hurt them.
…かもしれないな
Hypothetically, of course.
例えばの話だが
Well, yeah...
まあ そうですね
例えばの話ですけど
Hypothetically, of course.
だが考えるべきは
そこじゃない
But that's not what you need to think about.
In this case, what you should think about is why you
この場合 なぜ傷つけたくないか
こそを考えるべきなんだ
don't want to hurt them.
そして その答えはすぐに出る
And that answer will come to you immediately.
You don't want to hurt them because they're important to you.
大切なものだから 傷つけたくない
でもね 比企谷
But you know, Hikigaya...
傷つけないなんてことは
できないんだ
It's impossible not to hurt someone.
Humans unconsciously hurt others simply by existing.
人間 存在するだけで
無自覚に誰かを傷つけるものさ
Whether you're alive or dead, you keep hurting people.
生きていても死んでいても
ずっと傷つける
関われば傷つけるし
関わらないようにしても
Getting involved will hurt them,
but trying not to get involved might hurt them, too.
そのことが
傷つけるかもしれない
But if it's someone you don't care about,
けれど どうでもいい相手なら
傷つけたことに気づかない
you won't notice you've hurt them.
必要なのは自覚だ
What's important is your awareness of it.
大切に思うからこそ
傷つけてしまったと感じるんだ
It's because you care about them
that you feel like you've hurt them.
誰かを大切に思うということは
Caring about someone means
その人を傷つける覚悟をする
ということだよ
being resolved to the fact that you'll hurt them.
ヒントはここまで
That's your hint.
お互いが
お互いのことを思えばこそ
The more people care for each other,
手に入らないものもある
the farther out of reach certain things get.
But that's not something to be sad about.
けれど
それは悲しむべきことじゃない
I think it's probably something to be proud of.
たぶん誇るべきことなんだろうな
それってキツくないですか？
Isn't that kinda hard to do?
うん キツいな
Oh, yeah, it's hard.
But you can do it. I could, after all.
でもできる 私がそうだったからな
だからって 他のヤツにも
できるはずだっつうのは
It's a little arrogant to say someone else can do it just because you could.
ちょっと傲慢ですよ
かわいくないヤツめ うん？
You're so unlovable!
そうだな～
Okay...
正直に言おう
I'll be honest.
It probably doesn't have to be you, really.
たぶん
君でなくてもホントはいいんだ
この先 いつか
Someday,
Yukinoshita might change on her own.
雪ノ下自身が変わるかもしれない
いつか彼女のことを理解できる
人が現れるかもしれない
Someone might show up who can understand her.
彼女の元へ踏み込んでいく人が
いるかもしれない
Someone might get inside her.
The same can be said for Yuigahama.
それは 由比ヶ浜にも言えることだ
いつか… ですか？
Someday?
君達にとっては今 この時間が
全てのように感じるだろう
For you kids, right now feels like everything.
だが決して そんなことはない
But that's not true at all.
どこかで帳尻は合わせられる
At some point, everything will balance out.
世界は そういうふうにできている
That's how the world is made.
ただ 私はそれが
君だったらいいと思う
I just...
think it'd be nice if it could be you.
君と由比ヶ浜が 雪ノ下に踏み
込んでくれることを願っている
I'm hoping you and Yuigahama can get inside Yukinoshita.
いや
Still...
I don't really know what to...
そう言われても ちょっと
この時間が全てじゃない
Right now isn't everything,
but there are things you can only do now,
でも 今しかできないこと
ここにしかないものもある
and things you can only have here.
Now, Hikigaya. Now is the time.
今だよ 比企谷
今なんだ
Think. Agonize. Struggle. Worry.
考えて もがき苦しみ
あがいて悩め
そうでなくては
本物じゃない
Otherwise, it's not the real thing.
けど 苦しんだから
本物ってわけじゃないでしょ？
But...
Just because you suffered doesn't make it the real thing, does it?
Seriously, you're so unlovable.
ホントにかわいくないな 君は
<直近での
大きな障害となっているのは>
The biggest immediate obstacle is, obviously, the joint Christmas event.
<無論 クリスマス合同イベントだ>
Redial   Logs
<それに付随して
一色いろはの問題が出てくる>
The problem with Isshiki Iroha is attached to that.
Work Consulting on the Rise
<ここに
鶴見留美の現状も絡んでくる>
And the situation with Tsurumi Rumi ties into that.
Students' Plea for Help
Diversifying Communication
There are unexpected dangers?
<三つの問題の最適解は
どこにあるのか>
Where is the ideal solution to all three problems?
Dangers
I can't turn that situation around alone.
<俺一人で
ひっくり返すことはできない>
HELP
Should I ask someone for help?
<助けを求めるか？
なぜすぐに人に頼る？>
HELP
Discussion
Why do I immediately try to depend on someone else?
HELP
Discussion
COMMUNICATION
Connections between people are a narcotic.
Discussion
COMMUNICATION
<人と人とのつながりは
きっと麻薬だ>
COMMUNICATION
Discussion
Before you know it, you get hooked...
COMMUNICATION
<知らず知らず依存して
生徒会選挙の時の俺は>
When I was dealing with the election, Komachi gave me my reason.
<理由を与えてもらっていた
小町のために>
"It's for Komachi." I used that as a front to take action.
<そう建て前をつけて動き出した>
No, if I hadn't done that, I...
<いや そうでもしなければ俺は…>
<たぶん あの時の俺は
間違えたのだ そして今も>
I was probably wrong then.
And now, too.
<俺が見つけ出した俺の答え
俺の理由で動かなければ…>
The answer I found for myself...
I have to act for my own reasons.
Why didn't I want to let Yukinoshita or Yuigahama become president?
<雪ノ下と由比ヶ浜 二人を会長に
させたくなかったのはなぜか>
My true reason for acting, after getting a reason from someone else...
<動く理由をもらってまで
俺が動いた本当の理由>
<ほしいものがあったから>
Because there was something I wanted.
(ノック)
Come in.
どうぞ
(結衣)ヒッキー
Hikki...
どうしたの？
ノックなんかして
What's up? Why did you knock?
無理して
来なくてもいいと言ったじゃない
I told you that you didn't have to force yourself to attend anymore.
ちょっと用があってな
I had business here.
W-Want to sit down?
座ったら？
うん？
Is something wrong?
どうかしたの？
何か いつもと違くない？
You're not acting like usual...
(深呼吸)
一つ依頼がしたい
I want to make a request.
ヒッキー
ちゃんと話してくれるんだ
Hikki... You're going to talk to us?
一色の言ってたｸﾘｽﾏｽｲﾍﾞﾝﾄなんだが
It's about the Christmas event Isshiki brought up.
あれが想像以上にヤバくて
It's going a lot worse than I expected.
手伝ってもらいたいんだが
I'd like you to help.
けれど…
いや 言いたいことは分かる
But...
No, I know what you want to say.
I took this on myself.
俺が勝手にやったことだし それに
一色のためにならないとも言った
And I said our helping wouldn't help Isshiki.
ただ 一色を会長に推したのは俺だ
But I'm the one who pushed Isshiki to become president.
千葉村の小学生 覚えてるか？
あの子も参加してるんだが
Do you remember the kids from Chiba Village?
The girl from there is helping, but she's the same as back then.
相変わらずでな
ああ 留美ちゃんだっけ？
Oh.... Rumi-chan, was it?
That's why I want to do something.
だから何とかしたい
My own actions are the underlying cause.
俺が今までやってきたことが
遠因になってるし
I know I'm being selfish.
虫のいい話 してんのは分かってる
But still, I want to ask for your help.
それでも 頼みたい
あなたのせい
It's your fault.
…と そういうわけね？
That's what you're saying, correct?
ああ 否定はできない
Yeah. I can't deny that.
そう
I see.
あなた
一人の責任でそうなっているなら
If you caused these problems yourself,
あなた一人で
解決するべき問題でしょう
then I think you should solve them yourself.
だな
You're right.
Sorry. Forget I asked.
悪い 忘れてくれ
Wait!
待って そうじゃないよ
That's not true!
Why does it have to be like that?
何で そういうことになるの？
おかしいよ
It's not right!
いや おかしくはねえよ
No, it is right.
自分のことは自分で
当たり前のことなんだ
I should take care of my own problems.
That's how it works.
そうね
違うよ
That's right.
No, it's not! What you're both saying isn't right at all!
二人が言ってること
全然違うもん
Look, it's not just your fault, Hikki.
あのね ヒッキー
一人の責任じゃないんだよ
Maybe you're the one who came up with that stuff, and carried it all out...
考えたのはヒッキーだし
やったのもヒッキーかもしんない
でも私達もそうだよ
全部押しつけちゃったの
But we were wrong, too!
We forced it all onto you!
いや それは違うだろ
No, that's not true.
It is true!
違わない！ こうなってるのって
ヒッキーだけが悪いんじゃなくて
It's not just your fault things ended up this way!
It's my fault, too...
私もそうだし…
ゆきのんの言ってること
ちょっと ずるいと思う
I think what you said was a little unfair, Yukinon.
今 それを言うのね
You're saying this now?
あなたも卑怯だわ
You're unfair, as well.
Hang on. This isn't what I wanted to talk about.
待て そういう話が
したかったんじゃねえ
Yukinon, you didn't tell us anything.
ゆきのん 言わなかったじゃん
言ってくれなきゃ
分かんないことだってあるよ
There are things we can't know if you don't tell us.
あなただって言わなかった
You didn't say anything, either.
You only made conversation to keep up appearances.
ずっと取り繕った会話
ばかりしていた
So if that's what you...
だから あなたが
あなた達が望んでいるならって
そう…
If that's what both of you wanted, you...
言わないと分からない… か
...need to say so, or you'll never know?
でも 言われても
分かんねえことだってあるだろ？
But there are things you can't understand even if you're told, aren't there?
That's...
そんなこと…
Even if you'd told me, I probably wouldn't have accepted it.
言われても たぶん俺は
それに納得できないと思う
何か裏があるんじゃないかって
I would've thought there was something behind it,
事情があって
そう言ってるんじゃないかって
some circumstances making you talk that way,
even if it was my own selfish idea.
勝手に考えるかもしれない
でも その分
ちゃんと話せば
But if we'd talked about it...
ヒッキーと
もっと話せば私は…
If I had talked to you more... I...
I don't mean that.
そうじゃないんだ
言ったから分かるっていうのは
傲慢なんだよ
Saying you'd understand because you were told is arrogant.
言った本人の自己満足
It's an ego trip for the person who said it,
言われたヤツの思い上がり
or the conceit of the person who was told.
After things happen, there's no guarantee everyone will
色々あって 話せば必ず
理解し合えるってわけじゃない
understand if they talk about it.
だから
言葉がほしいんじゃないんだ
So what I want isn't words.
だけど言わなかったら
ずっと分かんないままだよ
But if you don't say anything, we'll never have any way to understand.
そうだな
You're right.
言わなくても
分かるっていうのは幻想だ
Thinking you'll understand without being told anything is an illusion.
でも…
But...
あッ
でも
But...
俺は…
I...
俺は
What I want isn't words.
<俺は言葉がほしいんじゃない>
What I wanted was definitely there.
<俺がほしかったものは
確かにあった>
And it wasn't mutual understanding,
<それはきっと分かり合いたいとか
仲良くしたいとか>
or to be friends, or to be together,
<一緒にいたいとか
そういうことじゃない>
or anything like that.
<俺は
分かってもらいたいんじゃない>
I don't want to be understood.
I want to understand.
<俺は分かりたいのだ>
I want to understand. I want to know.
<分かりたい 知っていたい
知って安心したい>
I want to feel at ease knowing.
I want peace of mind.
<安らぎを得ていたい 分からない
ことはひどく怖いことだから>
Because not understanding terrifies me.
Saying I want to understand everything is extremely self-righteous.
<完全に理解したいだなんて
ひどく独善的で独裁的で>
It's a dictatorial and conceited wish.
<傲慢な願いだ
ﾎﾝﾄにあさましくておぞましい>
It's shameless and repulsive.
<そんな願望を抱いてる自分が
気持ち悪くて仕方がない>
And I'm absolutely disgusted at myself for wanting that.
<だけど もしも
もしもお互いがそう思えるなら>
But if...
If we feel the same way...
<その醜い自己満足を
押しつけ合い>
If a relationship exists where we can force
that ugly self-consciousness upon each other, and accept it...
<許容できる関係性が
存在するなら>
<そんなこと
絶対にできないのは知っている>
I know there's no way that can happen.
<そんなものに
手が届かないのも分かっている>
I realize that's completely out of reach.
<それでも…>
But still...
それでも俺は
But still, I...
俺は
I...
I want
本物がほしい
the real thing!
ヒッキー
Hikki...
私には
I don't understand.
分からないわ
あ…
ごめんなさい
I'm sorry.
Yukinon!
ゆきのん！
ヒッキー 行かなきゃ
Hikki!
We have to go!
いや でも…
一緒に行くの
Uh, but...
We have to go together!
ゆきのん
分かんないって言ってた
Yukinon said she doesn't understand!
I think she just doesn't know what to do!
どうしていいかも
分かんないんだと思う
I have no idea, either, but...
私だって全然分かんない
But we can't let it end without ever knowing!
でも でも分かんないで
終わらせたらダメなんだよ
This is our only chance!
今しかない
あんなゆきのん 初めて見たから
I've never seen Yukinon act like that!
So we have to go now!
だから 今 行かなきゃ
あッ…
一人で歩けるからいい
It's okay. I can walk myself.
行くぞ
うん
Let's go.
Yeah!
Ah... um... I wanted to talk to you...
(いろは)あ… あの
声かけようと思ったんですけど
いろはちゃん
ごめん またあとでね
Sorry, Iroha-chan. Later, okay?
Senpai, there's no meeting today.
先輩 今日休みですから
I came to tell you that... a-and...
それを言いに あと…
分かった
Okay, got it.
Listen!
話 最後まで聞いてくださいよ
I'm not done talking.
雪ノ下先輩なら上です 上
If you're looking for Yukinoshita-senpai, she's on the roof.
悪い 助かる
Sorry. Thanks.
(走ってくる足音)
(ドアが開く)
(結衣の荒い呼吸)
Yukinon!
ゆきのん
私には分からない
I don't understand.
あなたの言う本物って
一体 何？
What do you mean by "the real thing"?
それは…
It's...
ゆきのん 大丈夫だよ
Yukinon, it's okay.
何が大丈夫なの？
What's okay?
I didn't really understand, either.
私も実は
よく分かんなかったから
だから 話せば
もっと分かるんだって思う
So I think,
if we talk, we'll understand more.
But we probably won't really understand even then, huh?
でも たぶん
それでも分かんないんだよね
それで
たぶん ずっと分かんないままで
And then we'd probably never understand...
だけど 何か
そういうのが分かるっていうか
But, like, we'd understand that... or something...
Nope, I guess I really don't get it.
やっぱり よく分かんないや
でもね
But...
I...
私さ
I don't like the way things are now.
私 今のままじゃヤダよ
なぜ あなたが泣くの？
Why are you the one crying?
やっぱり あなたって
You really are...
卑怯だわ
unfair.
(泣き続ける二人)
比企谷君
ああ
Hikigaya-kun.
Yeah?
あなたの依頼 受けるわ
I accept your request.
すまん
Thanks.
I'll help, too.
私も手伝う
助かる
I appreciate it.
#09     And so, Yukinoshita Yukino.
♬～
This beer is so good!
Man, I said some uncharacteristically awesome stuff there.
Go, me! I'm such a great teacher!
No... a great woman?
I'm a great woman, so why can't I get married?
Excuse me! The sampler, please!
And a husband, while we're at it! Just kidding...
Damn, Christmas already? Makes me sick...
If only I didn't have to work!
If I didn't have to work, I could go out for Christmas!
Excuse me! Highball, please!
I wanna get married...
(平塚)ビールがうまい
柄にもなく いい話してしまった➡
さすが私 いい教師だな～
いや いい女？➡
いい女なのに
何で結婚できないかな➡
すいません 鶏わさください
ついでに旦那もください➡
なんちゃって もうクリスマスか
気分悪い 仕事さえなければな➡
仕事さえなければ
ｸﾘｽﾏｽ遊びに行くんだけどな➡
すいません ハイボールください…
結婚したい